PROFESSOR: All right.
Now that we know what Markov decision
processes are, we can talk about how
to solve them.
For solving MDPs, there's a bunch of
important quantities we need to define
precisely so that we can come up with
algorithms that compute them.
Some of these quantities you already
know, or you know something
very much like them.
So the first one is the notion of the
utility or the value of a state s.
So you actually already know this.
This is just what would happen from
that state if you ran Expectimax.
And in particular, to define
it, we can write V* of s.
And what the star means is this is
the value under optimal action.
V* of s is the expected utility starting
in s and acting optimally.
The idea here is, if you act optimally
from s, sometimes you'll get big
rewards and sometimes you'll get small
rewards, because you don't actually
control your outcomes.
But on average, V* s is
the best you can do.
That is actually what
Expectimax computed.
So states have values which are
their Expectimax utilities.
Remember a q-state, s, a, is being in
the situation where you are in state s
and you are committed to action a,
but you haven't done it yet.
So anything could still happen.
The value or utility of a q-state
is written Q* of s comma a.
That is the expected utility from
that q-state if you act
optimally in the future.
Now if we think about this in
the tree, the values are
associated with states.
So we can write the value of a state and
say, that's what would happen if
you ran Expectimax from a state, meaning
you started out by picking the
best action and then recursed.
If, however, you run Expectimax starting
at a chance node, which here
are q-states, you would still get some
optimal thing, but it would be the
best you can do starting
at that chance node.
What does it mean to start at
a q-state or a chance node?
It means you are already
taking that action.
It's too late to decide a
wasn't the right thing.
Whatever is going to happen
is going to happen.
And then from s-prime forward,
you will behave optimally.
The third important quantity is pi*.
Pi is a policy.
Pi* is an optimal policy.
And pi* from s is the optimal
action from state s.
Let's take a look at what these
values actually are.
So here we see that same grid.
And now what's also shown are numbers
in the squares and arrows.
The arrows are easy.
The arrows are the policy
that has been computed.
And in this case, it's
the optimal policy.
Now in order to know whether we actually
got it right, I need to tell
you which setting of
grid world this is.
And in this case, this is a setting
where the living reward is minus 0.1.
And there's a small decay
or discount of 0.99.
So we can see the values of these
states, because the only thing that
can happen in these states is that you
choose exit, and then you get the
reward deterministically.
These states have values
of 1 and minus 1.
If you're down here in the lower left,
the policy suggests that you, over
time, make your way up and then over,
and then take the good exit.
This 0.49--
what's that?
That is, if you start in this state and
you ran this game over and over
again, and sometimes you slipped and
sometimes you didn't, and you added up
all of those utilities, on average
you would get 0.49.
And you would achieve it by trying
to go north whenever you
were in this state.
So you can see it's better to be
right here by the exit than it
is to be over here.
Why?
Because if you're over here, you have
to pay that living reward and some
discount to even get to the exit.
The best thing is actually
be in the exit.
Similarly, you can see, if you're
essentially two steps--
assuming nothing goes wrong--
from the exit, it's better to be up here
at 0.74 than down here at 0.57.
Because when something goes wrong
at 0.74, it's not a big deal.
When something goes wrong at 0.57,
you fall into the pit and lose.
So that's what the utilities
look like, and also the
policies on this grid.
So these are utilities.
These are the values of the states.
Let's in particular remember 0.57.
0.57 is the value of being in the state,
assuming you are smart in the
future, which means in particular
from the state going north.
What's this?
This is the q-values.
From each state, except for the
exit states, you've got
four choices of action.
If you are in this state where you're
between the wall and the pit, and the
action you've committed to is north,
then you get that same 0.57.
That's where the value comes from.
It comes from going north and
then acting optimally.
If, however, you're in the q-state of
being in this square and committing to
going right, your q-value is a lot
lower, because probably you're going
to fall into the pit.
Now, you might not.
And because of the definition of a
q-value, if you don't, you will then
act optimally in the future,
which will involve not
trying for the pit again.
But the point is each one of these
states has four q-values, but only one
value-- and unsurprisingly,
the value is going to be
the max of the q-values.
So we want to be able to
compute these things.
We'd like to be able to take an MDP and
compute these Expectimax values
for a state.
And actually, what we usually do with
these algorithms is we compute the
values for all of the states.
And we'll see that there are ways to
save time by doing all the states at
once, provided your MDP is small
enough that you can actually go
through all the states.
What are we computing?
We're computing the expecting utility
under optimal actions.
And that's going to be a sum
of discounted rewards.
Because this is what Expectimax
computed, we can write down a
mathematical definition of this thing
we're trying to compute that basically
parallels Expectimax, written
out in equations.
So where we used to have a recursive
function, now we're just going to have
equations that mention each other.
So let's take a look.
Well, from a state, we would
like to know, what is the
optimal value of a state?
That's Expectimax from
the root of the tree.
Well, what is it?
I'm not really sure, but I've got all
these actions I can choose from.
And I should maximize over them.
And I can write that as an equation,
as a max over the actions
available to me.
And for each action, if I go down in
the tree, I end up at a q-state.
And so I can essentially recurse.
What does that mean in an equation?
Well, I just write down the quantity
that's below, which is the value of a
state is the max over all the actions
available to you of the q-values, of
the chance nodes you would get if
you committed to that action.
That's just what the max function
of Expectimax did.
It's a max over all the chance nodes.
The tricky one, and the one that's
actually changed, is what do I do at a
chance node?
So in this case, I'm
here at s comma a.
And I want to know how many points I'm
going to get under optimal action.
It kind of depends what happens.
But I know what's going to happen.
Whatever state, s-prime, I land in,
I'm going to get some reward.
The reward is going to depend on s and
a, but also on whether or not the
outcome was good.
So the reward depends on
the whole transition.
That's going to be my one-time
step of reward.
But of course I'm going to
keep getting rewards from
s-prime when I land.
So I'm also going to get all of the
future rewards from s-prime.
But that's just a value.
So again, you see the
mutual recursion.
Now there's something missing here.
There's actually a couple
things missing here.
One thing that's missing is I don't know
which s-prime is going to happen.
And so at a chance node, what do I do?
What I do with all of these different
possible outcomes, s-prime?
I have to consider them all and I
have to take a weighted average.
And the way I write that in math is I
write that I'm going to sum up over
all s-primes.
And they each get a weight.
And that weight is given by
the transition function.
And it is the probability of s-prime,
given s and a, which we write as T of
s, a, s-prime.
So let's look at the pieces and
make sure we understand.
We're going to get a reward
in the next timestep, and
then a future reward.
They're going to be weighted by the
relative probabilities that come from
our transition function.
And we're missing one small
but important thing.
And that is V* is the score
we would get from s-prime.
But it's happening one timestep
in the future.
So it's worth less to me.
How much less?
Gamma less.
And now we have the recursive
expression for Q*.
And these are the pieces.
You have a reward and a future value.
You have a discount on
the future value.
And you have probabilities
that average together
the different outcomes.
So this expression may look complicated,
but you're going to be
seeing this so many times in so many
variations that it's important to make
sure you don't go into math shock
and you actually process it.
To that end, I am going to make
it appear in beautiful LaTeX.
Even though your code alternates between
maximizing in one function and
taking an average in another function,
it's often the case that
mathematically we essentially
inline q.
And we write the values V*
in terms of other values.
Let's try to do that.
Let's try to do it in one step.
I'm basically going to write the exact
same Expectimax recurrence.
I'm going to say, well, from here I
would get a reward on my transition,
and then a discounted future value
from wherever I land in s-prime.
And this would all depend
on which action I chose.
And I should choose the best one.
And it would depend on the
outcome of that action.
And so I need to take a weighted
average according to T.
So this is an expression of
values in terms of values.
As a function, it would
be mutually recursive.
As an equation, it's a
system of equations.
And because there's a max in
there, it's non-linear.
We'll come back to this
equation many times.
It's in fact what's called
a Bellman equation.
We'll be seeing this a lot
starting next lecture.
So here's that racing search tree.
And remember, we looked at this and we
said, all right, we just wrote some
equations, but they basically said
to run Expectimax, right?
You want the thing at the
root, so you take a max.
You want a chance node, so
you take an average.
Yeah, there was some discounting thrown
in, but I can do that with
Expectimax.
OK, fine.
But the racing tree is shown
here for two steps.
What happens if we go further?
Well, here, it looks like this.
It gets very big very quickly.
But if I look at this, I might think
that Expectimax is somehow a colossal
waste of time for this problem.
Why is Expectimax such a
colossal waste of time?
Basically, we're doing way too
much work with Expectimax.
And there's two reasons.
One reason why Expectimax is
wasting a lot of time is
that states are repeated.
So you look at this, you see that blue
car that's in the cool state over and
over and over, and the red car
over and over and over.
And somehow, we shouldn't be computing
that value over and over and over,
because it's always going
to be the same.
And this should remind you, basically,
of graph search.
We don't want to do the work again.
In addition to having lots of repeated
states, the tree also has the problem
that it's infinite, and it's hard
to compute infinite things.
So this tree goes on forever.
And we already have an idea for dealing
with infinite depth, and that
is, do something depth-limited.
But we need to be a little bit careful,
because we don't necessarily
know how deep we want to
go until we've done it.
But the basic idea is we're going
to do some kind of depth-limited
computation, and we'll increase the
depth until the change is small, and
then we'll say, OK, we're close enough,
and we'll declare victory.
Now the reason why that might work is
because, if we have a discount, gamma,
then as you go deeper into the tree,
you're seeing those same rewards-- the
plus 1's, the plus 2's,
the minus 10's--
except as they get buried deeper and
deeper in the tree, they start picking
up factors of gamma.
And if you go 100 steps into the tree,
they've got a gamma to the 100 in
front of them.
And so if you go deep enough into the
tree, even though the tree goes on
forever, eventually it stops
contributing very much, because it's
out of the agent's horizon
in a soft way.
All right.
So how can we not do Expectimax in a way
that does all this work over and
over again, and then never terminates
because the tree is infinite?
The key idea here is we'll have
time-limited values, which you can
think of as a stopwatch.
Even though this game might in fact go
on forever, we've got a stopwatch
that's counting down the number of
timesteps remaining until, as far as
the agent's concerned,
the end of days.
And you've got k steps remaining,
and then the game just stops.
So we can define here not V*, which
would be some optimal thing letting
the game run forever.
We can define something much more
concrete and easy to think about,
which is V sub k, the time-limited
value of a state.
V sub k is the optimal value
of s if the game ends after
exactly k more timesteps.
What's a timestep?
It's a reward.
So exactly k more rewards.
This is actually kind of nice, because
this is exactly what a depth-k
Expectimax would give if
we started it from s.
So if you think about this tree here,
this is not the whole tree from the
blue states.
However, this is a depth-2 tree.
There's two rewards.
Where do the rewards come?
This is actually pretty important.
The rewards come here when this chance
layer resolves, and they come here
when this chance layer resolves.
That's where the transitions are.
OK, this is V sub 2.
If I ran this Expectimax and
I truncated it after two
steps, I get V sub 2.
And because we're just truncating and
we're just ending the game, we don't
need an evaluation function, because
we don't have to talk about what
happens after the game ends.
Nothing happens.
There are no rewards after two steps.
So let's take a look at what these
V sub k's actually are.
Then we'll figure out how to compute
them, and that's going to give us an
important algorithm.
All right.
So let's look here.
What this shows right now is, from
each of the states, what you can
achieve under optimal play if you are
allowed to take zero more actions.
Well, if there are zero more timesteps,
I'm not getting any more
rewards, which means the pit, the
gem, the wall, whatever--
it's all zero.
What happens if I can
take one more step?
Well, what happens if I'm
in the good exit?
Well, I have time to take
exit and get my plus 1.
If I'm in the bad exit, I have time
to take exit and get my minus 1.
And from anywhere else,
what can I achieve?
Well, it depends on the living
reward, but let's imagine the
living reward is zero.
I can achieve zero.
If I switch to V sub 1, then you can
see here that we have a plus 1, a
minus 1, and a whole bunch of zeros.
So you can see that from this
ledge, we get a zero.
Because in one timestep,
what can I do?
I can move north, I can
jump into the pit.
It doesn't matter.
I can't get any of the plus
1's or minus 1's.
Even here, where I have time to get to
the good exit, I don't have time to
leave and get my reward.
If I'm allowed two timesteps, you can
see that from this square, I have time
with some probability to get into
the good exit and leave
and receive my reward.
From here, the ledge, I have time to do
various stupid things, like go into
the pit and receive a negative.
But that's not the optimal thing.
The optimal thing is anything else.
And so I have a zero.
But if I'm allowed three steps, I can
get some rewards even from there.
And four steps, and five steps.
How many steps would it take for this
start state, if the lower left is the
start state, to have a value V sub
k which is greater than zero?
Well the shortest way I could possibly
get to a positive reward is one, two,
three, four, five, and then
six to take the exit.
So I look at V sub 6.
I can see that I have now 0.34 here.
Now what happens if I
allow seven steps?
Is this 0.34 going to go up or
is it going to stay the same?
Well, if I'm allowed seven steps, I can
not only get there in the lucky
way where nothing goes wrong.
I can also get there in various ways
where something goes wrong once.
So in fact, if I go to depth
7, that will increase.
And if I go all the way to depth
100, then I start to see
the particular values.
And now at depth 100, because of the
specific settings of this problem,
most of the states are pretty good.
It's pretty much, as long as you're
not in the pit, you get
a reasonable value.
And of course, these actual numbers and
how quickly they get smaller as
you go away from the reward will depend
on the specific probabilities
involved and discounts and so on,
in the instance of grid world.
All right.
So we saw what these V sub k's are.
They are your Expectimax value under
optimal play if the game
ends after k steps.
Now we can go back and we can look at
this big Expectimax tree, and we can
think about how V sub k
relates to this tree.
Let's imagine that in fact this
is the whole tree and it
doesn't go down to infinity.
It's hard to fit infinite trees
onto your PowerPoint.
So if this is the whole tree and we
looked at the bottom, we would say,
all right, what is at the bottom?
Well, it's a huge number of states I
would have to check in Expectimax.
But there's kind of only three
things down there, right?
Because there's only three
states in this MDP.
And for each one of these,
it's a terminal state.
Nothing else happens,
so no more rewards.
And that means that I've got,
essentially, lots and lots of copies
of V0, lots of depth-zero Expectimax.
In fact, we know what V0 is.
It's zero for any state.
Now what's in this layer up here?
Well, if I look, again we've
got a bunch of repetitions.
But each one of these computations is
a depth-one Expectimax computation.
Which means, in fact, all we have
is a whole bunch of copies
of V1 in this layer.
And if we go up, we've got a whole
bunch of copies of V2.
And then a whole bunch
of copies of V3.
Except now we're actually close enough
to the top that it's not that many.
And then at the very top, we're
only computing one value.
But conceptually this top layer
is well-represented by the
collection of V4's.
So do you see how, at the bottom, even
though the tree has grown immensely,
it's still only three values?
And each layer is V sub
k for a larger k.
So this actually gives us an idea of how
we can compute these values in an
efficient way, where we don't get the
explosion in depth, because you can
see at the bottom it's no
worse than at the top.